Okay, today's דף Daf is דף מ. Daf Mem. We pick up
at the bottom of ל"ט עמוד ב Lamed Tet Amud Bet and
we're in the middle of discussion of ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim because
ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim is one of the things that have to
be said in Hebrew. And the גמרא Gemara says like this,
בזמן שהכהנים מברכים את העם. Bizman shehakohanim mevarhim et ha’am. The line
starts מברכים את העם, mevarhim et ha’am, it's about twenty lines from
the bottom, about three lines above the תוספות במנחתא. Tosafot Beminhasa. בזמן
שהכהנים מברכים את העם מה הם אומרים, Bizman shehakohanim mevarhim et ha’am
ma hem omrim, when the כהנים Kohanim are blessing the people what
do the people say? You know nowadays we sort of, there are
these things printed in the סידורים Siddurim to say that a פסוק
Passuk corresponds to each word, although a lot of people really they
just sort of scan it with their eyes. People say you're not
supposed to be talking and we'll get to a point about that
in a little bit,
but here there was an assumption that you would say something while
they're doing it and as we'll see something that relates to each
individual word but to the fact that you are being blessed by
the כהנים. Kohanim. This is during the blessing, not at the end
when you say אמן. Amen. So what do the people say? בזמן
שהכהנים מברכים את העם מה הם אומרים, Bizman shehakohanim mevarhim et ha’am
ma hem omrim, what do the people say? אמר רבי זירא אמר
רב חסדא ברכו ה' מלאכיו גיבורי כוח, Amar Rabbi Zeira amar Rav
Hisda Barechu Hashem malachav gibborei khoah, praise God His angels of great
strength they should praise God. ברכו ה' כל צבאיו משרתיו עושי רצונו,
Barechu Hashem kol tzeva'av meshartav osei retzono, all of the hosts should
praise
God, those who serve God who do God's will. ברכו ה' כל
מעשיו בכל מקומות ממשלתו ברכי נפשי את ה', Barechu Hashem kol ma'asav
bechol mekomot memshalto barchi nafshi et Hashem, blessed is God all of
God's creatures should bless
God, my soul shall bless God. So you are receiving a blessing
from God and then you are responding as it were in kind.
God is just, you know I am blessing you, the כהנים Kohanim
saying God will bless you, and you're responding you know God should
be blessed or all of everybody should give God a blessing.
And a way as we'll see in the גמרא Gemara in a
minute as a way of sort of showing how grateful you are
for receiving the blessing.
Okay. במוספי
דשבתא מה הם אומרים, Bemusfei deshabbata ma hem omrim, what would they
say by שבת מוסף Shabbas Musaf because that would be an extra
שמונה עשרה? Shemoneh Esrei? The assumption would be okay that you would
say it during you know שחרית Shacharis a normal שחרית Shacharis and
you don't say it at מעריב Maariv you don't do ברכת כהנים
Birchas Kohanim at night because of עבודה, Avodah, you don't do it
at מנחה Mincha because that would be later in the day and
the כהנים Kohanim might be drunk and this is also a type
of a שירות Sherus and עבודה Avodah and you can't do it
while you're drunk. But they would say it at מוסף. Musaf. So
given that now we're, so we've said what you said at a
normal שחרית, Shacharis, what would you say at מוסף? Musaf? אמר רבי
אסי שיר המעלות הנה ברכו את ה' כל עבדי ה'. Amar Rabbi
Assi Shir hama'alot hinei barechu et Hashem kol avdei Hashem. So there's
so you're going to do something similar about a blessing to God,
a song of ascent, behold bless God all who serve God. שאו
ידיכם קודש וברכו את ה', Se’u yedekhem kodesh uvarechu et Hashem, lift
up your hands and bless God. Now of course this שאו ידיכם
קודש Se’u yedekhem kodesh is very much you know evocative of the
ברכת כהנים. Birchas Kohanim. Of course this is blessing God and the
שאו ידיכם Se’u yedekhem here is that the blessing is given to
God whereas ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim is that they lift up their
hands and they bless the people and God's blessing goes to the
people, but it's a sort of nice mirror image. ברוך ה' מציון
שוכן ירושלים הללויה, Baruch Hashem mitziyon shokhen yerushalayim halleluyah,
blessed is God from Zion the one who dwells in Jerusalem, praise
God. Now that's actually skipping to another פרק Perek in תהילים. Tehillim.
So the גמרא Gemara says that third פסוק Passuk ולימא נמי יברכך
ה' מציון, Velimar nami yevarekhekha Hashem mitziyon,
God should bless you from Zion. דכתיב בהאי עניינא, Dechtiv behai inyana,
that’s in the same פרק. Perek. So you have three and if
you notice right each one is three ברכו’s. Barechu So logically one
corresponding to each פסוק, Passuk, each פסוק Passuk they would say a
different you know you're receiving a blessing and you say a distinct
way that people should bless God, blessed be God a different פסוק
Passuk for each one. That's logically although we'll see in the גמרא
Gemara in a second whether that was the way it was. So
here too on מוסף Musaf there would be three פסוקים Passukim of
blessing God. So why not get this third פסוק Passuk יברכך ה'
מציון Yevarekhekha Hashem mitziyon from the same פרק? Perek? Why did you
skip a פרק? Perek? אמר יהודה בריה דרבי שמעון בן פזי מתוך
שהתחיל בברכותיו של הקדוש ברוך הוא
מסיים בברכותיו של הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar Yehuda bereih deRabbi Shimon ben
Pazi mitoch shehitchil biverchotav shel Hakadosh Baruch Hu mesayem biverchotav shel Hakadosh
Baruch Hu, because you are doing is what you're saying is you
are blessing God. כהנים Kohanim are saying God should bless you, you're
receiving God's blessing, you in response are blessing God right? So ברכו
את ה', Barechu et Hashem, ברוך ה' מציון. Baruch Hashem mitziyon. So
the one that the גמרא Gemara asks you know is ברוך ה'
מציון Baruch Hashem mitziyon is again blessing God. יברכך ה' Yevarekhekha Hashem
is what the כהנים Kohanim are saying God should give you the
blessing not that you are blessing God. So we want to keep
it consistent.
Okay. במנחתא דתעניתא מאי? Beminhata deta’anita mai? How about
מנחה Mincha on a תענית? Taanis? You know if you know that
when do חזרת הש"ץ Hazaras Hashatz on a תענית Taanis at מנחה,
Mincha, you say the יברכך ה' וישמרך Yevarekhekha Hashem veyishmerekha you normally
don't and if we're in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael where they do
a ברכת כהנים Birchas Kohanim every day they do the ברכת כהנים
Birchas Kohanim itself not just the יברכך ה' Yevarekhekha Hashem you know
that the שליח ציבור Shliach Tzibbur says at מנחה Mincha because the
only reason you don't do it at מנחה Mincha is because כהנים
Kohanim might be drunk at that time. But now at a תענית
Taanis you're not concerned about that. So what do you do? אמר
רב אחא בר יעקב אם עוונינו ענו בנו ה' עשה למען שמך.
Amar Rav Aha bar Yaakov im avonenu anu vanu Hashem aseh lema'an
shemekha.
So it's interesting even though you're receiving a ברכה Bracha it's a
type of a תפילה Tefilla
for the fact of what you're doing the תענית Taanit for, you
know you want God to answer you for rain or whatever the
issue was. So if our because of our sins God please do
on your for your sake. מקווה ישראל מושיעו בעת צרה Mikveh Yisrael
moshio be'et tzarah the hope of Israel should answer at a time
of anguish. למה תהיה
כגר בארץ למה תהיה כאיש נדהם כגיבור. Lamah tihyeh kheger ba'aretz lamah
tihyeh khe’ish nidham kegibbor. Okay, why should you be like one who
does not respond? So it's actually quite interesting because as opposed to
receiving a blessing and then responding by giving a blessing, here because
it's תענית Taanit and there's a reason for the תענית, Taanit, you
are receiving a blessing and if you're in connection with God, you're
using this opening as an opportunity to, you know, to pray and
to importune God for the reason for the תענית. Taanit. So it's
a definitely a very different theme. Okay, now top of מ"א, Mem
Aleph, בנעילה דיומא דכיפורי מאי? Bi'ne'ila dyoma dikippuri mai? מה בנעילה דיום
כיפור? Ma bi'ne'ila d'Yom Kippur? Which is again, you would say, you
know, no concern about being drunk there, and you would do a
ברכת כהנים. Birchat Kohanim. So presumably again would be something distinct. תוספות
Tosafot asks why not say הא בנעילת דתענית Ha bi'ne'ilat d'Taanit that
they would say at תענית? Taanit?
Okay,
but it's meaning, quoting גמרא Gemara that they would do נעילה Ne'ila
by תענית, Taanit, which is not our practice, of course. מאי טעמא?
Mai Ta'ama? אמר מר זוטרא ואמרי לה במתניתא, Amar Mar Zutra v'amri
la b'matnita, הנה כי כן יבורך גבר ירא ה'. Hinei ki chen
yevorach gever yere Hashem. Behold as a, you know, as a person
who will be blessed, the one who fears
God. יברכך ה' מציון וראה בטוב ירושלים כל ימי חייך וראה בנים
לבניך שלום על ישראל. Yevarechecha Hashem miTziyon u're'e b'tuv Yerushalayim kol yimei
chayecha u're'e vanim livanecha shalom al Yisrael. Okay, so there you have
God blessing us, so it's again not returning with a blessing from
God, but it's the end of יום כיפור Yom Kippur and, you
know, the idea of forgiveness of sin, so we sort of reiterate
this, you know, I mean it's ירא ה', Yere Hashem, right? But
it's also so, striving for being God-fearing,
but receiving God's blessing, you know, and hopefully looking towards the year
and it should be a year filled with blessing. Okay. So, interesting,
only the normal one is responding to the blessing with a blessing.
היכן אומרם? Heichan omram? Now, how where would you say this, these
פסוקים pesukim that would be said when you receive the ברכת כהנים?
Birchat Kohanim? רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar אמר בין כל ברכה וברכה. amar
bein kol bracha u'vracha. Between the ברכה. bracha. Like maybe, you know,
after you've said אמן Amen and they, presumably this indicates that they
would do an איי איי איי ai ai ai or something like
that. So you say it between the ברכה. bracha. We'll see, we'll
see about whether you would be saying אמן Amen or not, whether
this was in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash or not, but between
each
ברכה. bracha. רב ששת Rav Sheshet אמר באזכרת השם. amar b'hazkarat Hashem.
When you say God's name. So it's a way of, you're mentioning
the God's name and God's name appears in each ברכה, bracha, so
in each of the פסוקים pesukim of ברכת כהנים, Birchat Kohanim, so
it is a responding to hearing God's name, especially makes sense if
we're talking about the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Now, פליגי בה רב
מר ורב זביד. Pligi ba Rav Mar u'Rav Zevid. חד אמר פסוקא
לקבל פסוקא. Chad amar pasuka likaval pasuka. One said what is probably,
you know, most likely, most reasonable, that if it's three פסוקים pesukim
that the כהנים Kohanim give you ברכה bracha and three פסוקים pesukim
that you're saying in response, you say one פסוק pasuk in response
to each פסוק pasuk that the כהן Kohen says. וחד אמר אכל
פסוקא אמר להו לכולהו. V'chad amar a'kol pasuka amar lehu l'chulhu. On
every פסוק pasuk the כהנים Kohanim say, you respond with all three
of these פסוקים pesukim of responding of blessing to God. Okay. So
now we have this idea that you would say these ברכות. brachot.
And between each ברכה bracha or when you heard שם השם. Shem
Hashem. Now, but what about אמן? Amen? What about ברוך שם כבוד?
Baruch Shem Kavod? Is this in the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? Is
this out of the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? So the גמרא Gemara
now discusses this. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא כל האומרם בגבולים אינו
אלא טועה. Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba kol ha'omram bi'gvulim eino ela
to'eh. If you say them outside the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you're
making a mistake. You only say them in the בית המקדש Beis
Hamikdash because of the power of hearing the explicit שם השם. Shem
Hashem. So it's not just receiving God's blessing, it's hearing שם השם,
Shem Hashem, so you have to respond ברכו את השם. Barechu et
Hashem. So it certainly makes sense according to the opinion that says
that you said it when God's name is mentioned. But even if
you say it at the end of the פסוק, pasuk, the power
of that sense of God's presence bestowing the blessing, you know, that
is what invokes a response of a blessing. Okay. So only in
the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Now again, it's interesting because we learned
in the משנה Mishna that you would not interrupt the ברכות. brachot.
The ברכה bracha would be said as one unit of three in
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash because there's no אמן Amen to interrupt
them. So, you know, if this is said when God's name is
said, it's not dividing the ברכות. brachot. But if it's said between
them, then that divides it into three separate ברכות. brachot. So it
doesn't fit so well in the משנה Mishna about the idea that
in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash it would be a unit of
three and this is not really discussed in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay.
אמר רבי חנינא בר פפא תדע, Amar Rabbi Chanina bar Pappa teda,
you should know, רבי חנינא בר פפא Rabbi Chanina bar Pappa disagreed,
and he says you should
know דבמקדש נמי לא מיבעי למימרינהו. di'bi'mikdash nami lo mibai l'meimreinhu. It's
not just that you shouldn't say it, that it's wrong to say
it outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. I really disagree with this,
he says. You know, we may acknowledge that it was said in
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but it shouldn't be said. It's not
appropriate, or I don't see how they would have allowed it. Anyway,
he says you should not be saying this. כלום יש לך עבד
שמברכין אותו והוא מחזיר? Clum yesh l'cha eved she'mevarchin oto v'hu machzir?
Well, I don't understand. Like, you know, does a slave receive a
blessing and not listening to the blessing and he's busy mumbling to
himself? Even if he's mumbling in response and in thanks, you know,
aren't you supposed to be listening to the blessing? Now that, now
that makes it sound like you would be saying this during the
blessing, which makes sort of sense because then it's not about the
אמן Amen and it's not about, you know, it sort of doesn't,
it's not on the same plane as the questions of אמן Amen
and ברוך שם כבוד. Baruch Shem Kavod. But the גמרא Gemara before
at least one opinion said it was between the ברכות. brachot. So
again this sort of makes sense if you're saying it during, continuously
during, or at the ברוך שם, Baruch Shem, doesn't make so much
sense if you're saying it between the ברכות. brachot. So the גמרא
Gemara doesn't really match these things up with the question of when.
Okay.
Now the גמרא... Gemara... This says like this, אמר רב יצחק בר
חנינא תדע דגל נמי בעי למימני. Amar Rav Yitzchak bar Chanina teda
de'gal nami baei lemimnei. He says actually, he says, I'm going to
say the opposite. It's appropriate to say it even out of the
בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, which is not our practice obviously. We do
not say these פסוקים, pesukim, as nobody noticed, we don't say these.
Okay, כלום יש עבד שמברכין אותו ואין מקביל פנים? Klum yesh eved
shemevarchin oso ve'ein maqbil panim? And
here's why I think you should be saying it, because it's not
about not paying attention and it's not necessarily needing to respond to
God's name. If you receive a blessing, then you have to show
how grateful you are for this blessing. And that of course would
make sense if it said between the ברכות. brachos. So
different explanations here might also be linked. The earlier explanations of only
in the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, it's distracting, you're not paying attention,
that makes sense if you're saying it at שם השם Shem Hashem
or during the ברכה. bracha. And this idea about you're appreciating it
and responding in kind makes sense if it's said between the ברכות.
brachot. Okay, אמר רבי אבהו מריש הוה אמינא להו, Amar Rabbi Abahu
merish hava amina lehu, I used to say these outside the בית
המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. כיון דחזיתיה לרבי אבא דמן עכו דלא אמר להו,
Keivan dechaziteih le'Rabbi Abba de'min Akko d'lo amar lehu, once I saw
Rabbi Abba from Akko who didn't say it, אנא נמי לא אמינא,
ana nami lo amina, I also don't say it. Why he gave
specific weight to Rabbi Abba, we'll see in a minute. He respected
him as a very humble man, but anyway somehow that impressed on
me that you should not be saying it. Okay, ואמר רבי אבהו,
Ve'amar Rabbi Abahu, Rabbi Abahu also said, מריש הוה אמינא ענוותנא אנא.
Merish hava amina anvetana ana.
I used to say that I thought I was a humble person,
a modest person. I didn't go around bragging that I was a
modest person, but I used to think that I was modest. כיון
דחזיתיה לרבי אבא דמן עכו דאמר איהו חד טעמא ואמר אמורא חד
טעמא, Keivan dechaziteih le'Rabbi Abba de'min Akko d'amar ihu chad ta'ama ve'amar
amora chad ta'ama,
because the אמורא, amora, you know, we use these words אמורא amora
and תנא. tana. And when we normally use it, תנא tana means
the rabbis of the משנה Mishna and the ברייתא Baraisa and אמורא
amora means the rabbis of the גמרא. Gemara. But they also really
refer to the sort of people that did more of a functionary
role. The תנאים Tannaim were the ones who memorized all the משניות
Mishnayos and ברייתות. Baraisos. They didn't author them, but they just were
walking books, repositories.
And that's why sometimes the גמרא Gemara says like 'the תנא Tana
taught', meaning he taught over the teaching he had memorized. And the
אמורא, amora, from the word, you know, תנא tana is like משנה
mishna to repeat, the אמורא amora is like אמירה amira to speak.
Right? He was the one that the rabbi from the time of
the גמרא Gemara would say something and then he would broadcast it.
He'd be the loudspeaker, you know, and make sure that everybody hears
it. So he says that this Rabbi Abba from Akko was so
humble that when he would tell his אמורא, amora, "Now explain to
the people, like here's the הלכה halacha and then he gave him
and here's the reason," and then the אמורא amora would give his
own reason. He figured, "Hey, I know this just as well as
Rabbi Abba from Akko knows it," so I'm just going to tell
them what I think the reason is. Maybe he wouldn't even say
that it was his own reason. It could be he said mine
plus his. It could be he said his instead of mine, like,
"Oh, Rabbi Abba says this, you know, but I think the reason
is that." In ways that's maybe even more חוצפה. chutzpah. Anyway, but
he would either add or replace his reason with mine, and that's
what would happen with Rabbi
Abba ולא קפיד ve'lo kapid and he said fine. He didn't feel
that it was a big deal. Now again, you know, you think
that Rabbi Abba, it's one thing to be humble, it's another thing
to have your responsibility of תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah to the people.
And if the people need to, you know, learn תורה Torah and
you think that your reason is the better one and your explanation
is the better one, so the only way I think it really
makes sense is that he added his own and maybe added his
own, this אמורא, amora, in his own name, because otherwise again, you
wouldn't want something that you didn't say ascribed to you. So the
way it makes sense that it's about humility but he wasn't concerned
about תלמוד תורה Talmud Torah is that the אמורא amora said, "Okay,
this is, I'm now announcing what Rabbi Abba said and now here's
what I say," and Rabbi Abba let him do it. He let
him use that platform ולא קפיד. ve'lo kapid. אמינא לאו ענוותנא אנא.
Amina lav anvetana ana. So I said I'm not really that humble.
Look, he's allowing him to really like put himself, his אמורא amora
to put himself equal to him, so I realized my sense of
what being humble was was not really
as humble as he was. ומאי ענוותנותיה דרבי אבהו? U'mai anvetanutheih de'Rabbi
Abahu? And where was the humility of Rabbi Abahu? What made Rabbi
Abahu think that he was being humble, showing proper humility? And we'll
see it's the same in the same type of issue but not
to the same degree.
What was his humility? דאמרה לה דביתהו דאמוריה דרבי אבהו לדביתהו דרבי
אבהו. De'amrah lah deveitehu de'amorieh de'Rabbi Abahu le'deveitehu de'Rabbi Abahu. The wife
of Rabbi Abahu's אמורא, amora, so again it's talking about their אמורות,
amoras, the, you know, their announcers, their loudspeakers, said to Rabbi Abahu's
wife, הדידן לא צריך ליה לדידך. Hadidan lo tzarich leih ledidach. You
know, ours doesn't need yours. My husband is a big enough rabbi,
he doesn't need your husband Rabbi Abahu. He can really go ahead,
he can give his own שיעור. shiur. He doesn't need Rabbi Abahu
to, to you know, tell him the תורה Torah that he's going
to repeat to the people. He can do it all on his
own. Okay. והא דגחין וזקפי עליה, V'had gochin v'zakfi aleh,
and the fact that he bends down to hear what Rabbi Abbahu
says and then stands up and announces it to the people, if
he's really able to do it all by himself, יקרא בעלמא הוא
דעביד ליה, Yekara b'alma hu d'avid leh, he's just a way of
showing him
respect to your husband to Rabbi Abbahu because Rabbi Abbahu was actually
close to the government, and to the authorities, so he's a way
of showing respect. But bottom line is he doesn't need him at
all, he could give a better שיעור shiur than your husband. אזלא
דביתיה ואמרה ליה לרבי אבהו, Azla deviteh v'amra leh l'Rabbi Abbahu,
so Rabbi Abbahu's wife went and told Rabbi Abbahu, this is you
should know this is what your אמורא Amora is telling his wife.
אמר לה מאי נפקא לך מינה, Amar lah mai nafka lach mina,
what do you care? מיני ומינה יתקלס עילאה, minei u'mineh yitkales ila'ah,
between me and him God's name is elevated.
So he wasn't מקפיד. makpid. Alright, let him say it's נארישקייט, narishkeit,
he wants to think he can give a good שיעור shiur as
me, who's it hurting? So here you see though why it's not
the same degree because this was just something he sort of said
to his wife, I could give just as good a שיעור shiur
as he does, I don't know why he has that position, but
it's not really putting himself in public on a similar footing. Who
knows, maybe he's going around telling other people this, but it's not
the same degree of putting himself on a similar footing as the
אמורא Amora of Rabbi Abba. So Rabbi Abbahu realized that he was
not at the same level of being willing to forgo his injury
to his honor. ותו V'su Rabbi Abbahu, מינו
רבנן ליה למימנייה ברישא, Minu rabanan leh l'minyei b'reisha,
here's another story. Rabbi Abbahu, the rabbis decided to make him the
ראש ישיבה. Rosh Yeshiva. כיון דחזא ליה לרבי אבא דמיעכו, Keivan d'chaza
leh l'Rabbi Abba d'me-Akko, but then he saw this Rabbi Abba from
Acco, דנפישי ליה בעלי חובות, d'nefishi leh ba'alei chovos, that he had
a lot of creditors, he owed a lot of money.
אמר להו, Amar lehu, איכא רבא, Ika raba, there's a greater rabbi,
you should actually have this Rabbi Abba from Acco be your ראש
ישיבה, Rosh Yeshiva, he's better for this than I am. And that
position came with apparently a lot of nice salary or a lot
of gifts and allowed him to pay off his creditors. Again, I
find this a little difficult because that's nice that he cares about
this guy's money,
but what about the תורה Torah that he owes the students? But
maybe this position was more about honor and less about really impacting
the תורה Torah that the students would learn. Not totally spelled out.
רבי אבהו ורבי חייא בר אבא איקלעו להוא אתרא. Rabbi Abbahu v'Rabbi
Chiya bar Abba ikla'u l'hu atra. Now Rabbi Abbahu and Rabbi Chiya
bar Abba came to a certain place. רבי אבהו דרש באגדתא. Rabbi
Abbahu darash b'agadata. So again, a story with Rabbi Abbahu. Rabbi Abbahu
gave a שיעור shiur in
אגדתא, Agadata, a nice little מדרש, Midrash, a sermon, a דבר תורה,
Dvar Torah, a good little message with a story. רבי חייא בר
אבא דרש בשמעתא. Rabbi Chiya bar Abba darash b'shmai'sa. Rabbi Chiya bar
Abba gave a really serious הלכה Halacha שיעור shiur with serious sources.
שבקו כולי עלמא לרבי חייא בר אבא ואזלו לגבי רבי אבהו. Shavku
kulei alma l'Rabbi Chiya bar Abba v'azlu legabei Rabbi Abbahu. Everybody left
Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, which was a really hard שיעור shiur and
very complicated, and they went to hear the nice אגדתא, Agadata, the
nice sermon meaningful message that Rabbi Abbahu had a share. חלש דעתיה,
Chalash dateh, so Rabbi Chiya bar Abba felt despondent. I had such
an amazing high level שיעור shiur and nobody wanted to hear it.
אמר ליה, Amar leh, so Rabbi Abbahu said to him, אמשול לך
משל למה הדבר דומה. Emshol lach mashal l'mah ha-davar domeh. Let me
give you an analogy, what is this similar to? לשני בני אדם,
L'shnei b'nei adam,
to two people. אחד מוכר אבנים טובות, Echad mocher avanim tovos, one
person is selling jewels, pearls, diamonds, ואחד מוכר מיני סידקית, v'echad mocher
minei sidkis,
and one person is selling little knickknacks. על מי קופצין, Al mi
koftzin,
now he's going and selling it in the village, where's everybody go?
It's nice to look at the diamonds and the pearls, but nobody
can actually afford them, so everybody's going to go, because everybody wants
to buy some of these little knickknacks and needles and whorls and
whatever they are. So על מי קופצין לאותו שמוכר מיני סידקית, Al
mi koftzin l'oso shemocher minei sidkis, everybody goes to the one selling
the tiny little items. So your שיעור shiur is obviously at a
much higher level, you're right, it's a very high level למדות, Lamdus,
גמרא, Gemara, הלכה Halacha שיעור, shiur, but it's far beyond these people.
So of course they're going to come to me, not that my
תורה Torah is better, but it's just more at their level. כל
יומא הוי מלוה רבי חייא בר אבא לרבי אבהו עד
אושפיזיה. Kol yoma havi melaveh Rabbi Chiya bar Abba l'Rabbi Abbahu ad
ushpizeh.
Every day Rabbi Chiya bar Abba would accompany Rabbi Abbahu until Rabbi
Abbahu's lodging place. Why? משום
יקרא דבי קיסר, mishum yekara d'vei Keisar, because as I mentioned before,
Rabbi Abbahu was close to the government, to the Caesar's house, and
therefore to show honor he would accompany him to the lodge where
he was staying when they would be at a village, presumably they
would stay at different lodgings. ההוא יומא, Hahu yoma, that day, in
order
to show Rabbi Chiya bar Abba that
he was such a big תלמיד חכם Talmid Chacham and he recognized
the level of Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, so what he did was
אלוייה רבי אבהו לרבי חייא בר אבא עד אושפיזיה. alviyeh Rabbi Abbahu
l'Rabbi Chiya bar Abba ad ushpizeh. So
Rabbi Abbahu accompanied Rabbi Chiya bar Abba to Rabbi Chiya bar Abba's
lodging to show him that he was attending to him and recognized
his greatness in
תורה. Torah. ואפילו הכי לא איתותב דעתיה מיניה, V'afilu hachi lo itosev
dateh mineh, and even so it did not sort of make him
feel that much
better because it's nice to be told you have amazing תורה, Torah,
but it's also nice to feel popular and that people want to
hear from you.
That was a little bit of a digression there about this whole
issue because we got on Rabbi Abbahu and Rabbi Abba. from עכו
Acco about whether you say these פסוקים pesukim during ברכת כהנים Birchas
Kohanim or not. Now בזמן שהשליח צבור אומר מודים העם מה הם
אומרים Bizman shehashaliach tzibbur omer modim ha'am mah hem omrim now
because we're talking about saying something when you're receiving ברכת כהנים, Birchas
Kohanim, we're going to say about saying something when you hear the
מודים modim that the שליח צבור shaliach tzibbur said. Now this is
quite interesting, right, because, you know, the גמרא Gemara focuses on two
key moments of שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei or חזרת הש"ץ Chazaras Hashas
that it's important to be there for. One is of course the
קדושה Kedusha and, you know, he's, you know, and everybody's saying קדוש
קדוש Kadosh Kadosh and sort of, you know, sanctifying God's name and
the ברכה beracha of האל הקדוש. Ha'el Hakadosh. And then the מודים
modim at the end when you thank and everybody is there to
also say מודים אנחנו Modim Anachnu to participate in that sense of
gratitude to God at the end of the שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh Esrei.
And so the assumption here is, as opposed to the ברכת כהנים
Birchas Kohanim you're receiving a ברכה beracha and you want to recognize
that you've received it and say something back, here there's an assumption
that you're going to say something at the time of the מודים
modim to show your, you know, your expressing this communal expression of
gratitude to God, you're echoing that that the שליח צבור shaliach tzibbur
is saying. So מה הם אומרים mah hem omrim what would they
say? אמר רב מודים אנחנו לך השם אלקינו על שאנו מודים לך.
Amar Rav Modim Anachnu Lach Hashem Elokeinu Al She'anu Modim Lach. You
got to love this, we thank you God that we are thanking
you. Meaning רש"י Rashi says we thank you that you have given
into us the, you know, the desire to thank you, the closeness
to you that we have been able to receive things that we're
able to thank you for. We're thanking you for the ability to
thank. Presumably because in your own שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei you already
thanked God for what you were davening for, now in the repetition
of the שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei the שליח צבור shaliach tzibbur saying
thank you and you're saying we are so thankful that we are
a people that pray to you and are able to give you
thanks for what you have done for us. ושמואל אמר אלקי כל
בשר על שאנו מודים לך. Ushmuel Amar Elokei Chol Basar Al She'anu
Modim Lach.
He elaborated it, God of all flesh, that we thank you. רבי
סימאי אמר יוצרנו יוצר בראשית Rabbi Simai Amar Yotzreinu Yotzer Bereshis also
elaborated on the, on the way of talking about God, creator of
all of creation, על שאנו מודים לך al she'anu modim lach that
we thank you for the fact that we thank you. נהרדעי אמרי
משמיה דרבי סימאי Nahardai Amri Mishmei DeRabbi Simai also, and now until
now they were just sort of, you know, descriptive of God, but
then here he's adding something, an additional thing that we are saying,
we're articulating, not just thanks for thanks, but ברכות והודאות לשמך הגדול
על שהחייתנו וקיימתנו Berachos Vehoda'os Lishmecha Hagadol Al Shehechiyanu Vekiyamtanu blessings and
thanks to your great name that you gave us life, על שאנו
מודים לך al she'anu modim lach
because we thank you. So now actually something a little more concrete,
you know, that you have given us our life, you know, very,
very concrete. רב אחא בר יעקב מסיים דרבי סימאי Rav Acha Bar
Yaakov Mesayem DeRabbi Simai
and he ended this addition of רבי סימאי Rabbi Simai the following
way, מסיים בהכי כן תחיינו ותחננו. Mesayem Behachi Kein Techayeinu Usechaneinu.
Now not only is it a concrete thanks for giving us life,
it's a בקשה. bakasha. So you should give us life and and
be kind to us ותקבצנו ואסוף גליותינו לחצרות קדשך, Vetiktatzeinu Vesof Galuyoseinu
Lechatzeros Kodshecha,
gather us to your בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, because מודים modim is
coming right after רצה, Retzei, ולשמור חקיך ולעשות רצונך בלבב שלם, Velishmor
Chukecha Vela'asos Retzonecha Belevav Shalem,
to observe and to do your, you know, your מצוות, mitzvos, על
שאנחנו מודים לך al she'anachnu modim lach and we thank you because
we thank you. So got a little bit, got a little all
filled up with other stuff, got a little off-topic. You know, there's,
you lose sort of sometimes I think when we say this מודים
modim what's called the מודים דרבנן, Modim Derabbanan, right, we lose this
power of מודים על שאנו מודים, Modim Al She'anu Modim, we're giving
thanks for the ability to give thanks, you know, and we sort
of because then it becomes the middle what בני אדם benei adam
makes it really just a, you know, a more normal type of
thank you, thank you for giving us life, a בקשה bakasha that
you should continue to give us life. Okay. אמר רב פפא הלכך
נימרינהו לכולהו. Amar Rav Pappa Hilkach Nimaninhu Lekulhu. Since these are all
nice things to say let's just bundle it all together, which is
what we do. אמר רבי יצחק לעולם תהא אימת צבור עליך. Amar
Rabbi Yitzchak Le'olam Tehei Eimat Tzibbur Alecha.
You should always feel if you're a, like, you know, a head
of a community, or leader, you should always respect, now it says
the fear, the אימה eima of the community should be on you,
but we'll see the גמרא Gemara makes this a little more general,
you should always sort of respect, you know, show proper כבוד kavod
to the community. שהרי כהנים פניהם כלפי העם אחוריהם כלפי שכינה. Sheharei
Kohanim Pnehem Klapei Ha'am Achoreihem Klapei Shechina.
When they bless the people they're turning their backs to, you know,
God as it were, you know, where the ארון Aron is, the
front of the שול shul and they're facing the people to show
respect to the people. That's how much the people are held in
respect. רב נחמן אמר מהכא Rav Nachman Amar Mehacha and that's why
we're mentioning it here because of ברכת כהנים. Birchas Kohanim. ויקם המלך
דוד על רגליו Vayakom Hamamelech David Al Raglav and the King David
got on his feet this one day they were collecting money for
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, ויאמר שמעוני אחי ועמי. Vayomer Shimuni Achai
Ve'ami.
Listen to me my people and my and my nation. אם אחי
im Achai if you're my brothers, you're my equals. למה עמי lamah
Ami why my nation? ואם עמי ve'im Ami
and if my nation, people I have control over, למה אחי lamah
Achai why referring to them as your equals, your brothers? אמר רבי
אלעזר אמר להם דוד לישראל, Amar Rabbi Elazar Amar Lahem David LeYisrael,
David said to the Jewish people, אם אתם שומעים לי אחי אתם.
Im Atem Shom'im Li Achai Atem. If you're prepared to listen to
me then I'll treat you as equals. So there's the כבוד kavod
to the צבור, tzibbur, not exactly the אימה eima from before. ואם
לאו עמי אתם. Ve'im Lav Ami Atem.
But if not you'll be, I'm going to force you to contribute
and I will show you that you are my people, you are
subject to me, my subjects. ואני רודה אתכם במקל. Va'ani Rodeh Eschem
Bemakkal. I'll use force. רבנן אמרי מהכא. Rabbanan Amri Mehacha. The רבנן
Rabbanan show from here, דתנו רבנן detanu Rabbanan we taught that what's
added, אין כהנים רשאים לעלות בסנדליהם לדוכן. Ein Kohanim Rashaim La'alos Besandaleihem
Laduchan. Bringing it back to ברכת כהנים, Birchas Kohanim,
the כהנים Kohanim cannot go up with to the דוכן duchan with
their sandals on. וזו אחת מתשע תקנות שתיקן יוחנן בן זכאי. Vezu
Achas Mitisha Takanos Shetikken Yochanan Ben Zakai. And one of the תקנות
takanos that... רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakai מאי טעמא
Mai ta'ama why
לאו משום כבוד ציבור Lav mishum kevod tzibur presumably it's כבוד ציבור
kevod tzibur because when they lift up their hands the hem of
their garment will lift up and you'll see their muddy sandals so
out of respect you know you want to take off your sandals
and presumably clean feet are better than muddy sandals. So so again
now we're back to כבוד הציבור kevod hatzibur not exactly אימת ציבור.
eimat tzibur. אמר רב אשי Amar Rav Ashi לא, lo, no that's
not what it's about. התם Hatam שמא נפסקה לו רצועה בסנדלו, shema
nifsika lei retzu'a besandalo, there the concern is that you'll be going
up to do ברכת כהנים Birkat Kohanim and your one of the
straps of your sandal will have snapped והדר אזיל למיקטריה ve-hadar azil
lemiktireih and then you're going to go back and you're going to
bend down and you're going to try knotting it while everybody else
is going up and doing ברכת כהנים Birkat Kohanim ואמרי בן גרושה
או בן חלוצה הוא ve-amri ben grusha o ben chalutza hu and
people will say oh you know he's not going up, אמת, emes,
look because he's trying to fix his shoe but really he's not
going up because he's a בן גרושה או בן חלוצה, ben grusha
o ben chalutza, he's not allowed to do ברכת כהנים. Birkat Kohanim.
So you don't want that to be the problem so you have
everybody take off their shoes. Okay back to the משנה. mishna. במקדש
ברכה אחת, Bamikdash bracha achat, in the מקדש Mikdash they would make
ברכת כהנים Birkat Kohanim one ברכה. bracha. וכל כך למה, Vechol kach
lama, now why would it be one ברכה bracha rather than three?
לפי שאין עונים אמן במקדש Lefi she'ein onim Amen bamikdash because you
don't say אמן Amen במקדש. bamikdash. So since you don't say אמן
Amen after each ברכה, bracha, we'll see why you don't in a
minute or whatever, we'll see a source for this, you they're not
broken up into three ברכות, brachot, they're said all three consecutive. Now
this is a little funny given the גמרא Gemara before thought said
that in the מקדש Mikdash you would say these פסוקים psukim you
know to break them up and we're also going to see that
you say ברוך שם כבוד מלכותו לעולם ועד Baruch shem kavod malchuto
leolam vaed in the מקדש Mikdash so תוספות Tosafot says well the
ברוך שם כבוד מלכותו Baruch shem kavod malchuto that you would say
maybe at שם השם Shem Hashem you wouldn't say it at the
end end of the ברכה bracha so it wouldn't break the ברכות
brachot up into three ברכות brachot
and presumably that works again with the idea that that's what you
do when you'd say the פסוקים psukim by שם השם. Shem Hashem.
But according to the opinion you say the פסוקים psukim between these
individual פסוקים psukim then it's again not clear why the משנה mishna
says that it was only going to be treated as one ברכה
bracha of three פסוקים psukim in the מקדש Mikdash rather than as
three separate ברכות. brachot. Okay so you don't say אמן Amen and
it doesn't break it up. תנו רבנן Tanu Rabbanan מניין שאין עונים
אמן במקדש minayin she'ein onim Amen bamikdash where do you see you
don't say it? שנאמר Shene'emar קומו ברכו את ה' אלהיכם, Kumu barchu
et Hashem Elokeichem, this is you know in Ezra where they say
get up and bless God this is in the בית המקדש Beit
Hamikdash מן העולם ועד העולם min haolam ve'ad haolam from this world
to the next so that's you know ברוך שם כבוד מלכותו לעולם
ועד Baruch shem kavod malchuto leolam vaed is seen as the liturgy
you know the sentence that encapsulates this idea and that's in the
בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. ומניין שעל כל ברכה וברכה תהילה Uminayin al
kol bracha ubaracha tehilla and how do you know that this is
what you respond for every individual ברכה? bracha? שנאמר Shene'emar ויברכו שם
כבודך veyivarchu shem kevodecha they will bless, end of the end of
the פסוק pasuk they bless your holy name, ומרומם על כל ברכה
ותהילה u-meromam al kol bracha u-tehilla and it be lifted up over
every ברכה bracha and praise. על כל ברכה וברכה תן לו תהילה
Al kol bracha u-varacha ten lo tehilla for every single ברכה bracha
give praise, so the praise though would be ברוך שם כבוד Baruch
shem kavod it would not be אמן. Amen. And again maybe because
ברוך שם כבוד Baruch shem kavod was around שם השם Shem Hashem
it would not break it up if you thought ברוך שם כבוד
Baruch shem kavod was at the end as a type of an
אמן, Amen, again it would raise the question why it would be
one ברכה bracha and not three. Now why you would not say
אמן Amen במקדש bamikdash is not exactly explained
the מהרש"א Maharsha explains that it has something to do with like
something about the גימטריא. gematria. I think a much better explanation is
that
אמן Amen just says that you are echoing, you know somebody else
has initiated and you say yes I agree with that too. Now
there's a power to be a follower, the גמרא Gemara discussing אמן
Amen speaks about the tremendous power it is. It's not just the
person who leads, it's everybody then who follows. But it could be
that in the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash when you're sort of directly
in the presence of God you know there you are supposed to
not just you know say yes I agree with that but you
are supposed to if you're going to say something about a blessing
of God you have to say a blessing as well. You have
to say blessed be God not just say אמן Amen to somebody
else's blessing. Okay we will end with that here.